Whyte, William Foote Additional Papers /4102
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
William Foote Whyte Additional Papers
1974-1988
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Whyte, William Foote
/4102
7 cubic feet
7 linear ft.
Papers (documents).
7984579
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
A. Holland-Loucks, June 17, 2011
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, September 30, 2016
Biographical / Historical
William Foote Whyte (June 27, 1914-July 16, 2000) was a sociologist chiefly known for his ethnographic study in urban sociology, Street Corner Society. Whyte, from an upper middle class background, showed an early interest in writing, economics and social reform. After graduating from Swarthmore College, he was selected for the Junior Fellows program, where his landmark research was done. After his research in Boston, he entered the sociology doctoral program at the University of Chicago. Street Corner Society was published by the University of Chicago Press in 1943. He spent a year teaching at the University of Oklahoma, but developed polio in 1943 and spent two years in physical therapy at the Warm Springs Foundation. Rehabilitation was only partially successful; Whyte walked with a cane for the rest of his life, and used two arm crutches in his later years. He briefly returned to the University of Chicago in 1944, then joined the New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations at Cornell University in 1948, remaining at Cornell for the remainder of his career. He worked for social reform and social change, directing his efforts toward "empowering the disenfranchized and narrowing the gap between rich and poor." He studied industrial and agricultural workers and workers' cooperatives in Venezuela, Peru, Guatemala and in the Basque region of Spain, as well as in the United States. He authored hundreds of articles and 20 books including an autobiography. He is considered a pioneer in industrial sociology.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /4149 AV: "ASA Award Presentation to William Foote Whyte by Jacqueline Scheier" Audio-Visual Materials /4149: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4151: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4163: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4168: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4173: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4087: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4094: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4058: William Foote Whyte Office Records
Whyte, William Foote, 1914-2000
7984579
- Evaluation Research on Federally Assisted Employee Buyouts, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- EDA Project Group, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Pacific Paperboard Products, Inc., 1977-1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Pacific Paperboard Products, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- EDA Correspondence Budgets, etc., 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- EDA Correspondence Day Hall Memos, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Economic Development Administration, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- EDA Memos, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Tim Kennedy, Chuck Craypo, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Pacific Paperboard Robert Pankin, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Pacific Paperboard Robert Pankin, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Democratic ESOP Robert Pankin, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- EDA Notes, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- EDA Buyout Reports, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Atlas Chain Robert Pankin, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Memos and Correspondence on Student Assistants, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Vouchers Travel, Phone, etc., 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- New Systems of Work and Participation, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- New Systems of Work and Participation Metro Grant, 1976-1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- National Institute of Mental Health, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- NIMH Ro1 MH29259-01, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- New Systems of Work and Participation Memos, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Budget, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- NIMH Grant Renewal, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Organizational & Community Employment Strategies: Final Report MH29529 Center for Work & Mental Health, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- NIMH Final Report Guidelines, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- DOL, NIMH, EDA Travel Vouchers (1 of 2), 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- DOL, NIMH, EDA Travel Vouchers (2 of 2), 1977 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- DOH Grant Applications, 1974-1977 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Budget Planning for Second Year, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Rethinking Ownership and Control Dissertation (1 of 2), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Rethinking Ownership and Control Dissertation (2 of 2), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Mohawk Valley Economic Development District Mohawk, NY, 1976-1979 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Mondragon, Spain, 1976-1980 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Norway Study, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Jamestown Project Interviews (1 of 2), 1978 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Jamestown Project Interviews (2 of 2), 1978 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Jamestown Project Faculty Dean, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Legislative Project NSWPP- Congressional, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Joyce Rothschild-Whitt Memos NSWPP, 1977-1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- NSWPP Book, 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Summer Plans and Other Commitments of Faculty on NSWPP, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Documentation Center, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Strongforce- cooperative firms, etc. Alix Simonetti, 1977-1981 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Byers Questionnaire, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Ithaca Gun, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Employee Stock Options, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Joyce Rothschild-Whitt, 1976-1980 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Program Plans, 1977-1982 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Williamson-Dickie Manufacturing Co. The "Executive Operations Technique" Program, 1978-1982 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- USDL Strengthening Local Economies 91-36-76-39, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Program on Comparative Economic Development, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- EDA, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Audio-Visual Program Documentary, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- National Endowment for the Humanities Budget, proposal, etc., 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- New Systems of Work and Participation Program Grant, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Applicant visas, job information, etc. for coordinator positions (NIMH project), 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- New Systems of Work and Participation, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Travel and related information Professional Trips Summer, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- New Systems of Work and Participation, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- APA Papers, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- International Sociological Assoc. Upsala Meeting, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- National Endowment for the Humanities Summer Seminars, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Isidor Walliman, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Meeting with Jamestown Group, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Symposium Communications Workers of America, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Cicione JET Homes, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Travel Vouchers (1 of 2), 1977-1979 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Travel Vouchers (2 of 2), 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- New School- Joyce, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Donna's Project, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Newsreel Project, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Don McCall Economic Development Program, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Article for Harvard Business Review, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- NSWPP Handbook, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- NSF Workshop Proposal, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- NSWPP Book- Chapters, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- University Technical Assistance- EDA, 1977-1979 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- NIMH Grant, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- NSWPP Vouchers MH29259-03, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- NSWPP Vouchers MH29259-03, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Employee Ownership Workshop, 1977-1979 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- HCI Post-Buyout Performance, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Revolving Loan Funds, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- PEWS and EDA Project, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Wynn Hausser, 1980-1984 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Wynn Hausser, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Christopher Meek (1 of 2), 1985 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Christopher Meek (2 of 2), 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Project Report, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Investigative Method, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Evaluation Research on Federally Assisted Employee Buyouts, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Cornell Draft, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Robert Stern, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- WFW Chapters 1-2 and Preliminary Report to EDA, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Bates Fabrics, Inc., 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Kostmayer Employee- Ownership Bill, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Legislative Project- Bill, Related Memos, Student Projects, etc., 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Testimony-Legislative Project Assorted Legislation, 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Memos from Whyte, 1978-1980 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Unemployment Insurance Compensation Proposal, 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Department of Labor Book Writing Project (1 of 2), 1980-1982 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Department of Labor- Book Writing Project (2 of 2), 1980 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Department of Labor Book Chapter 1, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Department of Labor Book Chapter 5, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Department of Labor Book Chapter 6, 1981-1982 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Seymour Lipset Articles on Social Status, Social Mobility, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Rath Packing Company, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Rath Packing Company Preliminary Report, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Rath II Documentary Panel Group, 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Rath Buyout, 1984-1986 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Rath Evaluation, 1982-1984 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Paul Goldman, Distribution Copy, 1982-1985 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Rath Conference Ford Foundation, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Proposal to the Ford Foundation, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Pamela Tolbert Distribution Copy, 1979-1981 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Rath Budget, 1982-1983 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Rath Conference (1 of 2), 1982 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Rath Conference (2 of 2), 1982 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Unfair Labor Practice Cases (1 of 2), 1982 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Unfair Labor Practice Cases (1 of 2), 1982 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Rath Project, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Rath Packing, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Rath, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Squire-Rath Material, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Squire-Rath Material, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Rath Meatpacking Plant, 1979-1981 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Saratoga Springs Knitting Mills (1 of 2), 1976-1981 (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Saratoga Springs Knitting Mills (2 of 2), 1976 (Box 7, Folder 16)